这是事情变得有点激烈的地方。
This is where things get a little bit intense.
所以我可以说我有一个函数转换器
So I can say I have a function transformer
比方说，一个任务，好吧。
of, let's say, a task, all right.
我们将其称为函数任务。
And we'll call this a function task.
然后我可以说我有一个变压器，好吧，让我们做，是的，
Then I could say I have an either transformer, well let's do, yeah,
让我们做一个变压器。
let's do an either transformer.
无论是功能任务的变换器，
Either transformer of function task,
[笑] 我们将其称为我的应用程序。
[LAUGH] and we'll call that my app.
好吧，这里发生了什么？
All right, what's happening here?
好吧，我在变压器内部的变压器堆栈中有一个变压器堆栈
Well, I have a transformer stack inside a transformer stack inside a transformer
堆叠在变压器堆叠内。
stack inside a transformer stack.
所以我的应用程序类型确实是，可能应该没有全部表达
So my app type really is, probably should be expressed without all
这些类型的变压器，因为我没有任何功能
these kind of transformers, as I haven't either holding a function
拿着任务，我想继续那个形状。
holding a task, and I'd like to just continue that shape.
假设我的应用程序可能不断出现错误，并且
Let's say my app just continually might have an error, and
如果是这样，我们只想停下来。
if it does we just wanna stop.
但是如果它没有继续前进，那么它内部就有一个函数
But if it doesn't keep going and then it has a function inside that which holds
一项任务，因为所有这些功能都只是做一些副作用，
a task, cuz all these functions just do side effecty things,
所以我们要早点绕道。
so we're gonna side circuit early.
我们有一堆函数，每个函数都在运行一个任务。
We have a bunch of functions and each of them is running a task.
因为那是我的应用程序的一种类型，对。
Cuz that's a type of my app right there, right.
这就是你将看到的基于 Monad 转换器的东西
And this is kind of what you're gonna see with these Monad transformer based
图书馆和
libraries and
函数式编程就是你得到这些类型的转换器堆栈。
functional programming is that you get these kind of stacks of transformers.
而且你必须弄清楚如何将你的东西放在正确的位置并抬起。
And you have to kind of figure out how to get your stuff in the right spot and lift.
那么让我们看看这是如何工作的。
So let's let's see how this works.
其实也没有试过T，[笑]所以让我们继续吧
Actually haven't tried either T, [LAUGH] so let's go ahead and
看看这里发生了什么。
see what's happening here.
我可能得换掉那个了。
I might have to swap that one out.
控制台记录，res，看看我们是否只是在原始水平上。
Console that log, res, see if we're just level on the original.
是的，它不起作用，好吧，让我们看看会发生什么。
Yeah, it's not working, all right, let's see what happens.
这不是正确的道路，好吧。
It's just not the right path, all righty.
好吧，那看起来很高兴。
Okay, so that seems happy.
所以我有两个应用程序，地图 xx 加一个。
so I have app of two, map x x plus one.
好的，所以这应该是三个，我有一个三个的应用程序。
Okay, so this should be three, I have an app of three.
好的，但什么是应用程序？
All right, but what is an app?
请记住，它是一个持有一个任务的函数。
Remember, it's an either holding a function holding a task.
所以让我们尝试获得这个值。
So let's try to get at this value.
所以我们将从 rez.fold 开始。
So we'll start with rez.fold.
如果我们得到一个错误，我会做一个错误。
I'll do just an error if we get one.
否则我们得到一个函数，好吧。
Otherwise we get a function out, all right.
让我们在一些感知环境中运行该函数。
Let's run that function with some perceived environment.
Myenv，真的。
Myenv, true.
好吧，这给了我一个任务。
All right, which gives me a task.
[笑] 让我们在这里给自己一些空间。
[LAUGH] Let's give ourself some room here.
是的，所以我们有了我们的功能，对不起，我们必须运行它，并且
Right, so we've got our function, I'm sorry, we have to run it, and
然后我得到了一个任务。
then I get a task out of that.
所以我可以分叉那个任务，我会console.error，然后我们会console.log。
So I can fork that task, I'll console.error, and then we'll console.log.
好的，所以我们有这个东西，它可以映射我想要的所有东西，并且
Okay, so we have this thing here that it can map over all I want, and
当我尝试运行它并查看会发生什么时。
when I tried to run it and see what happens.
我们得到一个值吗？
Do we get a value?
我们得到了三个，太棒了。
We get three out, terrific.
所以这只是与应用程序一起使用。
So that's just working with app.
挑战来自我们何时开始回归
And the challenges come from when we start to return eithers or
如果我们链接，这些东西中的功能或任务。
functions or tasks within these things if we chain.
所以我把三个案例放在链中。
So I put three cases in here of chain.
地图很棒，对，我只是做一些事情
Map is awesome, right, I just do stuff and
我什么都不用担心，它只是为我装瓶。
I don't have to worry about anything, it just bottles it right back up for me.
一旦我开始使用链条，
As soon as I start using chain,
我必须弄清楚我的函数会返回什么。
I have to figure out what is my function gonna return.
我们通常不会写这个，对，我们通常会说，
We're not usually writing this, right, we're usually saying,
链做数据库的事情，对吧。
chain do DB thing, right.
例如，这可能会返回一个任务。
That might return a task, for instance.
现在我必须弄清楚如何将我的任务放入一个函数中，在一个任务中，
Now I have to figure out how to get my task inside a function, inside a task,
要么在该任务中拥有它，等等。
either have it either inside that task and so on.
您将不得不手动将这些形状组合在一起。
You're gonna have to manually put these shapes together.
所以我向你展示的部分原因是因为
So part of the reason I'm showing you this is because
我不喜欢 Monad 变压器。
I don't love Monad transformers.
有时它们很有用，它们就在身边，很高兴知道，并且
Sometimes they're useful and they're around and it's good to know, and
如果你让它们保持浅薄，它们会有所帮助，
if you keep them shallow they can be helpful,
正如我们在另一个示例中看到的那样，但这不是我最喜欢的技术。
as we saw with the other example, but it's not my favorite technique.
所以让我们来看看第一件事。
So let's just walk through the first thing.
所以这个函数返回两个任务中的一个，我们必须进入我们的应用程序。
So this function returns a task either of two two, and we have to lift into our app.
这个下一个函数返回一个，然后我必须把它放在里面
This next function returns an either, which then I have to put inside
一个任务，我必须把它提升到那个，然后把它提升到应用程序中，对。
a task either, I have to lift it into that, and then lift that into app, right.
所以我的想法是我试图摆脱的形状是一个应用程序
So the idea is that my shape I'm trying to get out is an app
拿着一个任务拿着一个。
holding a task holding an either.
由于这个函数返回一个或者，我会把它提升到任务中并且
And since this function returns an either, I'll lift it into the task either and
将其提升到应用程序中。
lift that into an app.
接下来我们在这里讨论这个问题，然后
Next we go into this thing here, and
我正在返回一个任务，哎呀，一个任务。
I'm returning a task, whoops, a task.
现在我必须映射该任务并将其放入其中之一，所以我得到了一个任务
And now I have to map over that task and put it in an either, so I get a task
拿着四个中的一个，然后我把它放到应用程序中，依此类推。
holding an either of four, and then I lift that into the app, and so on.
有不同的方法，对吧，
There's different approaches, right,
我们可以映射到类型内部以将另一个类型放入其中，依此类推。
we can map to get inside the type to put another type inside it, and so on, etc.
但这就是事情变得非常棘手的地方。
But this is where things get really tricky.
我们只是，在我看来最好保持浅薄，没有大量的类型帮助。
And we just, it's best to stay shallow in my opinion without tons of type help.
还有一种叫做liftIO的东西。
There's also a thing called liftIO.
我什至不打算深入研究，但这可能会机械地推动你们所有人
I'm not gonna even go into it, but that can kind of mechanically push you all
到堆栈底部的方式，但我们不会处理它。
the way to the bottom of the stack, but we're not gonna deal with that.